<!-- Copyright (C) The IETF Trust (2011) -->
<!-- Copyright (C) The Internet Society (2011) -->

<section title="Acknowledgments">
  <t>
    The initial text for the SECINFO extensions were edited by Mike
    Eisler with contributions from Peng Dai, Sergey Klyushin, and Carl
    Burnett.
  </t>

  <t>
    The initial text for the SESSIONS extensions were edited by Tom
    Talpey, Spencer Shepler, Jon Bauman with contributions from Charles
    Antonelli, Brent Callaghan, Mike Eisler, John Howard, Chet Juszczak,
    Trond Myklebust, Dave Noveck, John Scott, Mike Stolarchuk, and Mark
    Wittle.
  </t>

  <t>
    Initial text relating to multi-server namespace features, including
    the concept of referrals, were contributed by Dave Noveck, Carl
    Burnett, and Charles Fan with contributions from Ted Anderson, Neil
    Brown, and Jon Haswell.
  </t>

  <t>
    The initial text for the Directory Delegations support were
    contributed by Saadia Khan with input from Dave Noveck, Mike Eisler,
    Carl Burnett, Ted Anderson, and Tom Talpey.
  </t>

  <t>
    The initial text for the ACL explanations were contributed by Sam
    Falkner and Lisa Week.
  </t>

  <t>
    The pNFS work was inspired by the NASD and OSD work done by Garth
    Gibson.  Gary Grider has also been a champion of high-performance
    parallel I/O. Garth Gibson and Peter Corbett started the pNFS effort
    with a problem statement document for the IETF that formed the basis
    for the pNFS work in NFSv4.1.
  </t>

  <t>
    The initial text for the parallel NFS support was edited by Brent
    Welch and Garth Goodson.  Additional authors for those documents were
    Benny Halevy, David Black, and Andy Adamson.  Additional input came
    from the informal group that contributed to the construction of the
    initial pNFS drafts; specific acknowledgment goes to Gary Grider,
    Peter Corbett, Dave Noveck, Peter Honeyman, and Stephen Fridella.
  </t>

  <t>
    Fredric Isaman found several errors in draft versions of the ONC RPC
    XDR description of the NFSv4.1 protocol.
  </t>

  <t>
    Audrey Van Belleghem provided, in numerous ways, essential
    co-ordination and management of the process of editing the specification
    documents.
  </t>

  <t>
    Richard Jernigan gave feedback on the file layout's striping pattern
    design.
  </t>

  <t>
    Several formal inspection teams were formed to review various areas
    of the protocol.  All the inspections found significant errors and
    room for improvement.  NFSv4.1's inspection teams were:
  </t>

  <t>
    <list style='symbols'>
      <t>
        ACLs, with the following inspectors: Sam Falkner, Bruce Fields,
        Rahul Iyer, Saadia Khan, Dave Noveck, Lisa Week, Mario Wurzl, and
        Alan Yoder.
      </t>

      <t>
        Sessions, with the following inspectors: William Brown, Tom
        Doeppner, Robert Gordon, Benny Halevy, Fredric Isaman, Rick
        Macklem, Trond Myklebust, Dave Noveck, Karen Rochford, John Scott,
        and Peter Shah.
      </t>

      <t>
        Initial pNFS inspection, with the following inspectors: Andy
        Adamson, David Black, Mike Eisler, Marc Eshel, Sam Falkner, Garth
        Goodson, Benny Halevy, Rahul Iyer, Trond Myklebust, Spencer
        Shepler, and Lisa Week.
      </t>

      <t>
        Global namespace, with the following inspectors: Mike Eisler, Dan
        Ellard, Craig Everhart, Fredric Isaman, Trond Myklebust, Dave
        Noveck, Theresa Raj, Spencer Shepler, Renu Tewari, and Robert
        Thurlow.
      </t>

      <t>
        NFSv4.1 file layout type, with the following inspectors: Andy
        Adamson, Marc Eshel, Sam Falkner, Garth Goodson, Rahul Iyer, Trond
        Myklebust, and Lisa Week.
      </t>

      <t>
        NFSv4.1 locking and directory delegations, with the following
        inspectors: Mike Eisler, Pranoop Erasani, Robert Gordon, Saadia
        Khan, Eric Kustarz, Dave Noveck, Spencer Shepler, and Amy Weaver.
      </t>

      <t>
        EXCHANGE_ID and DESTROY_CLIENTID, with the following inspectors:
        Mike Eisler, Pranoop Erasani, Robert Gordon, Benny Halevy, Fredric
        Isaman, Saadia Khan, Ricardo Labiaga, Rick Macklem, Trond
        Myklebust, Spencer Shepler, and Brent Welch.
      </t>

      <t>
        Final pNFS inspection, with the following inspectors: Andy
        Adamson, Mike Eisler, Mark Eshel, Sam Falkner, Jason Glasgow,
        Garth Goodson, Robert Gordon, Benny Halevy, Dean Hildebrand, Rahul
        Iyer, Suchit Kaura, Trond Myklebust, Anatoly Pinchuk, Spencer
        Shepler, Renu Tewari, Lisa Week, and Brent Welch.
      </t>
    </list>
  </t>

  <t>
    A review team worked together to generate the tables of assignments
    of error sets to operations and make sure that each such assignment
    had two or more people validating it.  Participating in the process
    were Andy Adamson, Mike Eisler, Sam Falkner, Garth Goodson, Robert
    Gordon, Trond Myklebust, Dave Noveck, Spencer Shepler, Tom Talpey,
    Amy Weaver, and Lisa Week.
  </t>

  <t>
    Jari Arkko, David Black, Scott Bradner, Lisa Dusseault, Lars Eggert,
    Chris Newman, and Tim Polk provided valuable review and guidance.
  </t>

  <t>
    Olga Kornievskaia found several errors in the SSV specification.
  </t>

  <t>
    Ricardo Labiaga found several places where the use of RPCSEC_GSS was
    underspecified.
  </t>

  <t>
    Those who provided miscellaneous comments include: Andy Adamson,
    Sunil Bhargo, Alex Burlyga, Pranoop Erasani, Bruce Fields, Vadim
    Finkelstein, Jason Goldschmidt, Vijay K. Gurbani, Sergey Klyushin,
    Ricardo Labiaga, James Lentini, Anshul Madan, Daniel Muntz, Daniel
    Picken, Archana Ramani, Jim Rees, Mahesh Siddheshwar, Tom Talpey, and
    Peter Varga.
  </t>
</section>
