<!-- Copyright (C) The IETF Trust (2011) -->
<!-- Copyright (C) The Internet Society (2011) -->

  <section anchor="op_LOOKUPP" title="Operation 16: LOOKUPP - Lookup Parent Directory">
    <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:op_LOOKUPP:A" title="ARGUMENT">
      <figure>
        <artwork>
/* CURRENT_FH: object */
void;
        </artwork>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:op_LOOKUPP:R" title="RESULT">
      <?rfc include='autogen/lookupp_res.xml'?>
    </section>

    <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:op_LOOKUPP:D" title="DESCRIPTION">
      <t>
        The current filehandle is assumed to refer to a regular directory or
        a named attribute directory.  LOOKUPP assigns the filehandle for its
        parent directory to be the current filehandle.  If there is no parent
        directory, an NFS4ERR_NOENT error must be returned.  Therefore,
        NFS4ERR_NOENT will be returned by the server when the current
        filehandle is at the root or top of the server's file tree.
      </t>

      <t>
        As is the case with LOOKUP, LOOKUPP will also cross mountpoints.
      </t>

      <t>
        If the current filehandle is not a directory or named attribute
        directory, the error NFS4ERR_NOTDIR is returned.
      </t>

      <t>
        If the requester's security flavor does not match that configured for
        the parent directory, then the server SHOULD return NFS4ERR_WRONGSEC
        (a future minor revision of NFSv4 may upgrade this to MUST) in the
        LOOKUPP response.  However, if the server does so, it MUST support
        the SECINFO_NO_NAME operation (<xref target="op_SECINFO_NO_NAME" />), so that the client can
        gracefully determine the correct security flavor.
      </t>

      <t>
        If the current filehandle is a named attribute directory that is
        associated with a file system object via OPENATTR (i.e., not a
        sub-directory of a named attribute directory), LOOKUPP SHOULD
        return the filehandle of the associated file system object.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:op_LOOKUPP:I" title="IMPLEMENTATION">
      <t>
        An issue to note is upward navigation from named attribute
        directories.  The named attribute directories are essentially
        detached from the namespace, and this property should be safely
        represented in the client operating environment.  LOOKUPP on a named
        attribute directory may return the filehandle of the associated file,
        and conveying this to applications might be unsafe as many
        applications expect the parent of an object to always be a directory.
        Therefore, the client may want to hide the parent of named attribute
        directories (represented as ".." in UNIX) or represent the named
        attribute directory as its own parent (as is typically done for the
        file system root directory in UNIX).
      </t>
    </section>
  </section>

