<!-- Copyright (C) The IETF Trust (2011) -->
<!-- Copyright (C) The Internet Society (2011) -->

  <section anchor="op_GETATTR" title="Operation 9: GETATTR - Get Attributes">
    <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:op_GETATTR:A" title="ARGUMENT">
      <?rfc include='autogen/getattr_args.xml'?>
    </section>

    <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:op_GETATTR:R" title="RESULT">
      <?rfc include='autogen/getattr_res.xml'?>
    </section>

    <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:op_GETATTR:D" title="DESCRIPTION">
      <t>
        The GETATTR operation will obtain attributes for the file system
        object specified by the current filehandle.  The client sets a bit in
        the bitmap argument for each attribute value that it would like the
        server to return.  The server returns an attribute bitmap that
        indicates the attribute values that it was able to return, which will
        include all attributes requested by the client that are attributes
        supported by the server for the target file system.  This bitmap is
        followed by the attribute values ordered lowest attribute number
        first.
      </t>

      <t>
        The server MUST return a value for each attribute that the client
        requests if the attribute is supported by the server for the target
        file system.  If the server does not support a particular attribute
        on the target file system, then it MUST NOT return the attribute
        value and MUST NOT set the attribute bit in the result bitmap.  The
        server MUST return an error if it supports an attribute on the target
        but cannot obtain its value.  In that case, no attribute values will
        be returned.
      </t>

      <t>
        File systems that are absent should be treated as having support for
        a very small set of attributes as described in <xref target="ss:multi-server_namespace:GwaAFS" />, even
        if previously, when the file system was present, more attributes were
        supported.
      </t>

      <t>
        All servers MUST support the REQUIRED attributes as specified in
        <xref target="ss:file_attributes:RALaDR" />, for all file systems, with the exception of absent file
        systems.
      </t>

      <t>
        On success, the current filehandle retains its value.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:op_GETATTR:I" title="IMPLEMENTATION">
      <t>
        Suppose there is an OPEN_DELEGATE_WRITE delegation held by another
        client for the file in question and size and/or change are among the
        set of attributes being interrogated.  The server has two choices.
        First, the server can obtain the actual current value of these
        attributes from the client holding the delegation by using the
        CB_GETATTR callback.  Second, the server, particularly when the
        delegated client is unresponsive, can recall the delegation in
        question.  The GETATTR MUST NOT proceed until one of the following
        occurs:
      </t>

      <t>
        <list style='symbols'>
          <t>
            The requested attribute values are returned in the response to
            CB_GETATTR.
          </t>

          <t>
            The OPEN_DELEGATE_WRITE delegation is returned.
          </t>

          <t>
            The OPEN_DELEGATE_WRITE delegation is revoked.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>
        Unless one of the above happens very quickly, one or more
        NFS4ERR_DELAY errors will be returned while a delegation is
        outstanding.
      </t>
    </section>
  </section>

