<!-- Copyright (C) The IETF Trust (2011) -->
<!-- Copyright (C) The Internet Society (2011) -->

  <section anchor="op_CREATE" title="Operation 6: CREATE - Create a Non-Regular File Object">
    <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:op_CREATE:A" title="ARGUMENT">
      <?rfc include='autogen/create_args.xml'?>
    </section>

    <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:op_CREATE:R" title="RESULT">
      <?rfc include='autogen/create_res.xml'?>
    </section>

    <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:op_CREATE:D" title="DESCRIPTION">
      <t>
        The CREATE operation creates a file object other than an ordinary
        file in a directory with a given name.  The OPEN operation MUST be
        used to create a regular file or a named attribute.
      </t>

      <t>
        The current filehandle must be a directory: an object of type NF4DIR.
        If the current filehandle is an attribute directory (type
        NF4ATTRDIR), the error NFS4ERR_WRONG_TYPE is returned.  If the
        current file handle designates any other type of object, the error
        NFS4ERR_NOTDIR results.
      </t>

      <t>
        The objname specifies the name for the new object.  The objtype
        determines the type of object to be created: directory, symlink, etc.
        If the object type specified is that of an ordinary file, a named
        attribute, or a named attribute directory, the error NFS4ERR_BADTYPE
        results.
      </t>

      <t>
        If an object of the same name already exists in the directory, the
        server will return the error NFS4ERR_EXIST.
      </t>

      <t>
        For the directory where the new file object was created, the server
        returns change_info4 information in cinfo.  With the atomic field of
        the change_info4 data type, the server will indicate if the before
        and after change attributes were obtained atomically with respect to
        the file object creation.
      </t>

      <t>
        If the objname has a length of zero, or if objname does not obey the
        UTF-8 definition, the error NFS4ERR_INVAL will be returned.
      </t>

      <t>
        The current filehandle is replaced by that of the new object.
      </t>

      <t>
        The createattrs specifies the initial set of attributes for the
        object.  The set of attributes may include any writable attribute
        valid for the object type.  When the operation is successful, the
        server will return to the client an attribute mask signifying which
        attributes were successfully set for the object.
      </t>

      <t>
        If createattrs includes neither the owner attribute nor an ACL with
        an ACE for the owner, and if the server's file system both supports
        and requires an owner attribute (or an owner ACE), then the server
        MUST derive the owner (or the owner ACE).  This would typically be
        from the principal indicated in the RPC credentials of the call, but
        the server's operating environment or file system semantics may
        dictate other methods of derivation.  Similarly, if createattrs
        includes neither the group attribute nor a group ACE, and if the
        server's file system both supports and requires the notion of a group
        attribute (or group ACE), the server MUST derive the group attribute
        (or the corresponding owner ACE) for the file.  This could be from
        the RPC call's credentials, such as the group principal if the
        credentials include it (such as with AUTH_SYS), from the group
        identifier associated with the principal in the credentials (e.g.,
        POSIX systems have a user database <xref target="openg_getpwnam" /> that has a group identifier
        for every user identifier), inherited from the directory in which the
        object is created, or whatever else the server's operating
        environment or file system semantics dictate.  This applies to the
        OPEN operation too.
      </t>

      <t>
        Conversely, it is possible that the client will specify in
        createattrs an owner attribute, group attribute, or ACL that the
        principal indicated the RPC call's credentials does not have
        permissions to create files for.  The error to be returned in this
        instance is NFS4ERR_PERM.  This applies to the OPEN operation too.
      </t>

      <t>
        If the current filehandle designates a directory for which another
        client holds a directory delegation, then, unless the delegation is
        such that the situation can be resolved by sending a notification,
        the delegation MUST be recalled, and the CREATE operation MUST NOT
        proceed until the delegation is returned or revoked.  Except where
        this happens very quickly, one or more NFS4ERR_DELAY errors will be
        returned to requests made while delegation remains outstanding.
      </t>

      <t>
        When the current filehandle designates a directory for which one or
        more directory delegations exist, then, when those delegations
        request such notifications, NOTIFY4_ADD_ENTRY will be generated as a
        result of this operation.
      </t>

      <t>
        If the capability FSCHARSET_CAP4_ALLOWS_ONLY_UTF8 is set
        (<xref target="ss:internationalization:UC" />), and a symbolic link is being created, then the
        content of the symbolic link MUST be in UTF-8 encoding.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:op_CREATE:I" title="IMPLEMENTATION">
      <t>
        If the client desires to set attribute values after the create, a
        SETATTR operation can be added to the COMPOUND request so that the
        appropriate attributes will be set.
      </t>
    </section>
  </section>

