<!-- Copyright (C) The IETF Trust (2011) -->
<!-- Copyright (C) The Internet Society (2011) -->

  <section anchor="op_CLOSE" title="Operation 4: CLOSE - Close File">
    <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:op_CLOSE:A" title="ARGUMENT">
      <?rfc include='autogen/close_args.xml'?>
    </section>

    <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:op_CLOSE:R" title="RESULT">
      <?rfc include='autogen/close_res.xml'?>
    </section>

    <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:op_CLOSE:D" title="DESCRIPTION">
      <t>
        The CLOSE operation releases share reservations for the regular or
        named attribute file as specified by the current filehandle.  The
        share reservations and other state information released at the server
        as a result of this CLOSE are only those associated with the supplied
        stateid.  State associated with other OPENs is not affected.
      </t>

      <t>
        If byte-range locks are held, the client SHOULD release all locks
        before sending a CLOSE.  The server MAY free all outstanding locks on
        CLOSE, but some servers may not support the CLOSE of a file that
        still has byte-range locks held.  The server MUST return failure if
        any locks would exist after the CLOSE.
      </t>

      <t>
        The argument seqid MAY have any value, and the server MUST ignore
        seqid.
      </t>

      <t>
        On success, the current filehandle retains its value.
      </t>

      <t>
        The server MAY require that the combination of principal, security
        flavor, and, if applicable, GSS mechanism that sent the OPEN request
        also be the one to CLOSE the file.  This might not be possible if
        credentials for the principal are no longer available.  The server
        MAY allow the machine credential or SSV credential (see
        <xref target="op_EXCHANGE_ID" />) to send CLOSE.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:op_CLOSE:I" title="IMPLEMENTATION">
      <t>
        Even though CLOSE returns a stateid, this stateid is not useful
        to the client and should be treated as deprecated.  CLOSE "shuts
        down" the state associated with all OPENs for the file by a
        single open-owner.  As noted above, CLOSE will either release
        all file-locking state or return an error.  Therefore, the stateid
        returned by CLOSE is not useful for operations that follow.  To
        help find any uses of this stateid by clients, the server SHOULD
        return the invalid special stateid (the "other" value is zero
        and the "seqid" field is NFS4_UINT32_MAX, see <xref target="ss:state_management:SS1" />).
      </t>

      <t>
        A CLOSE operation may make delegations grantable where they were not
        previously.  Servers may choose to respond immediately if there are
        pending delegation want requests or may respond to the situation at a
        later time.
      </t>
    </section>
  </section>

