<!-- Copyright (C) The IETF Trust (2011) -->
<!-- Copyright (C) The Internet Society (2011) -->

  <section anchor="op_LINK" title="Operation 11: LINK - Create Link to a File">
    <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:op_LINK:A" title="ARGUMENT">
      <?rfc include='autogen/link_args.xml'?>
    </section>

    <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:op_LINK:R" title="RESULT">
      <?rfc include='autogen/link_res.xml'?>
    </section>

    <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:op_LINK:D" title="DESCRIPTION">
      <t>
        The LINK operation creates an additional newname for the file
        represented by the saved filehandle, as set by the SAVEFH operation,
        in the directory represented by the current filehandle.  The existing
        file and the target directory must reside within the same file system
        on the server.  On success, the current filehandle will continue to
        be the target directory.  If an object exists in the target directory
        with the same name as newname, the server must return NFS4ERR_EXIST.
      </t>

      <t>
        For the target directory, the server returns change_info4 information
        in cinfo.  With the atomic field of the change_info4 data type, the
        server will indicate if the before and after change attributes were
        obtained atomically with respect to the link creation.
      </t>

      <t>
        If the newname has a length of zero, or if newname does not obey the
        UTF-8 definition, the error NFS4ERR_INVAL will be returned.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:op_LINK:I" title="IMPLEMENTATION">
      <t>
        The server MAY impose restrictions on the LINK operation such that
        LINK may not be done when the file is open or when that open is done
        by particular protocols, or with particular options or access modes.
        When LINK is rejected because of such restrictions, the error
        NFS4ERR_FILE_OPEN is returned.
      </t>

      <t>
        If a server does implement such restrictions and those restrictions
        include cases of NFSv4 opens preventing successful execution of a
        link, the server needs to recall any delegations that could hide the
        existence of opens relevant to that decision.  The reason is that
        when a client holds a delegation, the server might not have an
        accurate account of the opens for that client, since the client may
        execute OPENs and CLOSEs locally.  The LINK operation must be delayed
        only until a definitive result can be obtained.  For example, suppose
        there are multiple delegations and one of them establishes an open
        whose presence would prevent the link.  Given the server's semantics,
        NFS4ERR_FILE_OPEN may be returned to the caller as soon as that
        delegation is returned without waiting for other delegations to be
        returned.  Similarly, if such opens are not associated with
        delegations, NFS4ERR_FILE_OPEN can be returned immediately with no
        delegation recall being done.
      </t>

      <t>
        If the current filehandle designates a directory for which another
        client holds a directory delegation, then, unless the delegation is
        such that the situation can be resolved by sending a notification,
        the delegation MUST be recalled, and the operation cannot be
        performed successfully until the delegation is returned or revoked.
        Except where this happens very quickly, one or more NFS4ERR_DELAY
        errors will be returned to requests made while delegation remains
        outstanding.
      </t>

      <t>
        When the current filehandle designates a directory for which one or
        more directory delegations exist, then, when those delegations
        request such notifications, instead of a recall, NOTIFY4_ADD_ENTRY
        will be generated as a result of the LINK operation.
      </t>

      <t>
        If the current file system supports the numlinks attribute, and other
        clients have delegations to the file being linked, then those
        delegations MUST be recalled and the LINK operation MUST NOT proceed
        until all delegations are returned or revoked.  Except where this
        happens very quickly, one or more NFS4ERR_DELAY errors will be
        returned to requests made while delegation remains outstanding.
      </t>

      <t>
        Changes to any property of the "hard" linked files are reflected in
        all of the linked files.  When a link is made to a file, the
        attributes for the file should have a value for numlinks that is one
        greater than the value before the LINK operation.
      </t>

      <t>
        The statement "file and the target directory must reside within the
        same file system on the server" means that the fsid fields in the
        attributes for the objects are the same.  If they reside on different
        file systems, the error NFS4ERR_XDEV is returned.  This error may be
        returned by some servers when there is an internal partitioning of a
        file system that the LINK operation would violate.
      </t>

      <t>
        On some servers, "." and ".." are illegal values for newname and the
        error NFS4ERR_BADNAME will be returned if they are specified.
      </t>

      <t>
        When the current filehandle designates a named attribute directory
        and the object to be linked (the saved filehandle) is not a named
        attribute for the same object, the error NFS4ERR_XDEV MUST be
        returned.  When the saved filehandle designates a named attribute and
        the current filehandle is not the appropriate named attribute
        directory, the error NFS4ERR_XDEV MUST also be returned.
      </t>

      <t>
        When the current filehandle designates a named attribute directory
        and the object to be linked (the saved filehandle) is a named
        attribute within that directory, the server may return the error
        NFS4ERR_NOTSUPP.
      </t>

      <t>
        In the case that newname is already linked to the file represented by
        the saved filehandle, the server will return NFS4ERR_EXIST.
      </t>

      <t>
        Note that symbolic links are created with the CREATE operation.
      </t>
    </section>
  </section>

