<!-- Copyright (C) The IETF Trust (2011) -->
<!-- Copyright (C) The Internet Society (2011) -->

  <section anchor="op_CB_RECALL_SLOT" title="Operation 10: CB_RECALL_SLOT - Change Flow Control Limits">
    <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:op_CB_RECALL_SLOT:A" title="ARGUMENT">
      <?rfc include='autogen/cb_recall_slot_args.xml'?>
    </section>

    <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:op_CB_RECALL_SLOT:R" title="RESULT">
      <?rfc include='autogen/cb_recall_slot_res.xml'?>
    </section>

    <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:op_CB_RECALL_SLOT:D" title="DESCRIPTION">
      <t>
        The CB_RECALL_SLOT operation requests the client to return session
        slots, and if applicable, transport credits (e.g., RDMA credits for
        connections associated with the operations channel) of the session's
        fore channel.  CB_RECALL_SLOT specifies rsa_target_highest_slotid,
        the value of the target highest slot ID the server wants for the
        session.  The client MUST then progress toward reducing the session's
        highest slot ID to the target value.
      </t>

      <t>
        If the session has only non-RDMA connections associated with its
        operations channel, then the client need only wait for all
        outstanding requests with a slot ID > rsa_target_highest_slotid to
        complete, then send a single COMPOUND consisting of a single SEQUENCE
        operation, with the sa_highestslot field set to
        rsa_target_highest_slotid.  If there are RDMA-based connections
        associated with operation channel, then the client needs to also send
        enough zero-length "RDMA Send" messages to take the total RDMA credit
        count to rsa_target_highest_slotid + 1 or below.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:op_CB_RECALL_SLOT:I" title="IMPLEMENTATION">
      <t>
        If the client fails to reduce highest slot it has on the fore channel
        to what the server requests, the server can force the issue by
        asserting flow control on the receive side of all connections bound
        to the fore channel, and then finish servicing all outstanding
        requests that are in slots greater than rsa_target_highest_slotid.
        Once that is done, the server can then open the flow control, and any
        time the client sends a new request on a slot greater than
        rsa_target_highest_slotid, the server can return NFS4ERR_BADSLOT.
      </t>
    </section>
  </section>

