<!-- Copyright (C) The IETF Trust (2011) -->
<!-- Copyright (C) The Internet Society (2011) -->

<section anchor="sec:iana_considerations" title="IANA Considerations">
  <t>
    This section uses terms that are defined in <xref target="RFC5226" />.
  </t>

  <section anchor="ss:iana_considerations:NAD" title="Named Attribute Definitions">
    <t>
      IANA created a registry called the "NFSv4 Named Attribute Definitions
      Registry".
    </t>

    <t>
      The NFSv4.1 protocol supports the association of a file with zero or
      more named attributes.  The namespace identifiers for these
      attributes are defined as string names.  The protocol does not define
      the specific assignment of the namespace for these file attributes.
      The IANA registry promotes interoperability where common interests
      exist.  While application developers are allowed to define and use
      attributes as needed, they are encouraged to register the attributes
      with IANA.
    </t>

    <t>
      Such registered named attributes are presumed to apply to all minor
      versions of NFSv4, including those defined subsequently to the
      registration.  If the named attribute is intended to be limited to
      specific minor versions, this will be clearly stated in the
      registry's assignment.
    </t>

    <t>
      All assignments to the registry are made on a First Come First Served
      basis, per Section 4.1 of <xref target="RFC5226" />.  The policy for each assignment is
      Specification Required, per Section 4.1 of <xref target="RFC5226" />.
    </t>

    <t>
      Under the NFSv4.1 specification, the name of a named attribute can in
      theory be up to 2^32 - 1 bytes in length, but in practice NFSv4.1
      clients and servers will be unable to handle a string that long.
      IANA should reject any assignment request with a named attribute that
      exceeds 128 UTF-8 characters.  To give the IESG the flexibility to
      set up bases of assignment of Experimental Use and Standards Action,
      the prefixes of "EXPE" and "STDS" are Reserved.  The named attribute
      with a zero-length name is Reserved.
    </t>

    <t>
      The prefix "PRIV" is designated for Private Use.  A site that wants
      to make use of unregistered named attributes without risk of
      conflicting with an assignment in IANA's registry should use the
      prefix "PRIV" in all of its named attributes.
    </t>

    <t>
      Because some NFSv4.1 clients and servers have case-insensitive
      semantics, the fifteen additional lower case and mixed case
      permutations of each of "EXPE", "PRIV", and "STDS" are Reserved
      (e.g., "expe", "expE", "exPe", etc. are Reserved).  Similarly, IANA
      must not allow two assignments that would conflict if both named
      attributes were converted to a common case.
    </t>

    <t>
      The registry of named attributes is a list of assignments, each
      containing three fields for each assignment.
    </t>

    <t>
      <list style='numbers'>
        <t>
          A US-ASCII string name that is the actual name of the attribute.
          This name must be unique.  This string name can be 1 to 128 UTF-8
          characters long.
        </t>

        <t>
          A reference to the specification of the named attribute.  The
          reference can consume up to 256 bytes (or more if IANA permits).
        </t>

        <t>
          The point of contact of the registrant.  The point of contact can
          consume up to 256 bytes (or more if IANA permits).
        </t>
      </list>
    </t>

    <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:iana_considerations:IR" title="Initial Registry">
      <t>
        There is no initial registry.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:iana_considerations:UR" title="Updating Registrations">
      <t>
        The registrant is always permitted to update the point of contact
        field.  Any other change will require Expert Review or IESG Approval.
      </t>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section anchor="ss:iana_considerations:DIN" title="Device ID Notifications">
    <t>
      IANA created a registry called the "NFSv4 Device ID Notifications
      Registry".
    </t>

    <t>
      The potential exists for new notification types to be added to the
      CB_NOTIFY_DEVICEID operation (see <xref target="op_CB_NOTIFY_DEVICEID" />).  This can be done
      via changes to the operations that register notifications, or by
      adding new operations to NFSv4.  This requires a new minor version of
      NFSv4, and requires a Standards Track document from the IETF.
      Another way to add a notification is to specify a new layout type
      (see <xref target="ss:iana_considerations:LT" />).
    </t>

    <t>
      Hence, all assignments to the registry are made on a Standards Action
      basis per Section 4.1 of <xref target="RFC5226" />, with Expert Review required.
    </t>

    <t>
      The registry is a list of assignments, each containing five fields
      per assignment.
    </t>

    <t>
      <list style='numbers'>
        <t>
          The name of the notification type.  This name must have the
          prefix "NOTIFY_DEVICEID4_".  This name must be unique.
        </t>

        <t>
          The value of the notification.  IANA will assign this number, and
          the request from the registrant will use TBD1 instead of an
          actual value.  IANA MUST use a whole number that can be no higher
          than 2^32-1, and should be the next available value.  The value
          assigned must be unique.  A Designated Expert must be used to
          ensure that when the name of the notification type and its value
          are added to the NFSv4.1 notify_deviceid_type4 enumerated data
          type in the NFSv4.1 XDR description (<xref target="I-D.ietf-nfsv4-rfc5662bis-dot-x" />), the result continues
          to be a valid XDR description.
        </t>

        <t>
          The Standards Track RFC(s) that describe the notification.  If
          the RFC(s) have not yet been published, the registrant will use
          RFCTBD2, RFCTBD3, etc. instead of an actual RFC number.
        </t>

        <t>
          How the RFC introduces the notification.  This is indicated by a
          single US-ASCII value.  If the value is N, it means a minor
          revision to the NFSv4 protocol.  If the value is L, it means a
          new pNFS layout type.  Other values can be used with IESG
          Approval.
        </t>

        <t>
          The minor versions of NFSv4 that are allowed to use the
          notification.  While these are numeric values, IANA will not
          allocate and assign them; the author of the relevant RFCs with
          IESG Approval assigns these numbers.  Each time there is a new
          minor version of NFSv4 approved, a Designated Expert should
          review the registry to make recommended updates as needed.
        </t>
      </list>
    </t>

    <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:iana_considerations:IR1" title="Initial Registry">
      <t>
        The initial registry is in <xref target='devnotelist' />.  Note that the next available
        value is zero.
      </t>

      <texttable title="Initial Device ID Notification Assignments" anchor="devnotelist">
        <ttcol>Notification Name</ttcol>
        <ttcol>Value</ttcol>
        <ttcol>RFC</ttcol>
        <ttcol>How</ttcol>
        <ttcol>Minor Versions</ttcol>
        <c>NOTIFY_DEVICEID4_CHANGE</c> <c>1</c> <c>RFC5661</c> <c>N</c> <c>1</c>
        <c>NOTIFY_DEVICEID4_DELETE</c> <c>2</c> <c>RFC5661</c> <c>N</c> <c>1</c>
      </texttable>
    </section>

    <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:iana_considerations:UR1" title="Updating Registrations">
      <t>
        The update of a registration will require IESG Approval on the advice
        of a Designated Expert.
      </t>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section anchor="ss:iana_considerations:ORT" title="Object Recall Types">
    <t>
      IANA created a registry called the "NFSv4 Recallable Object Types
      Registry".
    </t>

    <t>
      The potential exists for new object types to be added to the
      CB_RECALL_ANY operation (see <xref target="op_CB_RECALL_ANY" />).  This can be done via
      changes to the operations that add recallable types, or by adding new
      operations to NFSv4.  This requires a new minor version of NFSv4, and
      requires a Standards Track document from IETF.  Another way to add a
      new recallable object is to specify a new layout type (see
      <xref target="ss:iana_considerations:LT" />).
    </t>

    <t>
      All assignments to the registry are made on a Standards Action basis
      per Section 4.1 of <xref target="RFC5226" />, with Expert Review required.
    </t>

    <t>
      Recallable object types are 32-bit unsigned numbers.  There are no
      Reserved values.  Values in the range 12 through 15, inclusive, are
      designated for Private Use.
    </t>

    <t>
      The registry is a list of assignments, each containing five fields
      per assignment.
    </t>

    <t>
      <list style='numbers'>
        <t>
          The name of the recallable object type.  This name must have the
          prefix "RCA4_TYPE_MASK_".  The name must be unique.
        </t>

        <t>
          The value of the recallable object type.  IANA will assign this
          number, and the request from the registrant will use TBD1 instead
          of an actual value.  IANA MUST use a whole number that can be no
          higher than 2^32-1, and should be the next available value.  The
          value must be unique.  A Designated Expert must be used to ensure
          that when the name of the recallable type and its value are added
          to the NFSv4 XDR description <xref target="I-D.ietf-nfsv4-rfc5662bis-dot-x" />, the result continues to be a
          valid XDR description.
        </t>

        <t>
          The Standards Track RFC(s) that describe the recallable object
          type.  If the RFC(s) have not yet been published, the registrant
          will use RFCTBD2, RFCTBD3, etc. instead of an actual RFC number.
        </t>

        <t>
          How the RFC introduces the recallable object type.  This is
          indicated by a single US-ASCII value.  If the value is N, it
          means a minor revision to the NFSv4 protocol.  If the value is L,
          it means a new pNFS layout type.  Other values can be used with
          IESG Approval.
        </t>

        <t>
          The minor versions of NFSv4 that are allowed to use the
          recallable object type.  While these are numeric values, IANA
          will not allocate and assign them; the author of the relevant
          RFCs with IESG Approval assigns these numbers.  Each time there
          is a new minor version of NFSv4 approved, a Designated Expert
          should review the registry to make recommended updates as needed.
        </t>
      </list>
    </t>

    <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:iana_considerations:IR2" title="Initial Registry">
      <t>
        The initial registry is in <xref target="recalllist" />.  Note that the next available
        value is five.
      </t>
      <texttable title="Initial Recallable Object Type Assignments" anchor="recalllist">
        <ttcol>Recallable Object Type Name</ttcol>
        <ttcol>Value</ttcol>
        <ttcol>RFC</ttcol>
        <ttcol>How</ttcol>
        <ttcol>Minor Versions</ttcol>
        <c>RCA4_TYPE_MASK_RDATA_DLG</c> <c>0</c> <c>RFC5661</c> <c>N</c> <c>1</c>
        <c>RCA4_TYPE_MASK_WDATA_DLG</c> <c>1</c> <c>RFC5661</c> <c>N</c> <c>1</c>
        <c>RCA4_TYPE_MASK_DIR_DLG</c> <c>2</c> <c>RFC5661</c> <c>N</c> <c>1</c>
        <c>RCA4_TYPE_MASK_FILE_LAYOUT</c> <c>3</c> <c>RFC5661</c> <c>N</c> <c>1</c>
        <c>RCA4_TYPE_MASK_BLK_LAYOUT</c> <c>4</c> <c>RFC5661</c> <c>L</c> <c>1</c>
        <c>RCA4_TYPE_MASK_OBJ_LAYOUT_MIN</c> <c>8</c> <c>RFC5661</c> <c>L</c> <c>1</c>
        <c>RCA4_TYPE_MASK_OBJ_LAYOUT_MAX</c> <c>9</c> <c>RFC5661</c> <c>L</c> <c>1</c>
      </texttable>
    </section>

    <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:iana_considerations:UR2" title="Updating Registrations">
      <t>
        The update of a registration will require IESG Approval on the advice
        of a Designated Expert.
      </t>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section anchor="ss:iana_considerations:LT" title="Layout Types">
    <t>
      IANA created a registry called the "pNFS Layout Types Registry".
    </t>

    <t>
      All assignments to the registry are made on a Standards Action basis,
      with Expert Review required.
    </t>

    <t>
      Layout types are 32-bit numbers.  The value zero is Reserved.  Values
      in the range 0x80000000 to 0xFFFFFFFF inclusive are designated for
      Private Use.  IANA will assign numbers from the range 0x00000001 to
      0x7FFFFFFF inclusive.
    </t>

    <t>
      The registry is a list of assignments, each containing five fields.
    </t>

    <t>
      <list style='numbers'>
        <t>
          The name of the layout type.  This name must have the prefix
          "LAYOUT4_".  The name must be unique.
        </t>

        <t>
          The value of the layout type.  IANA will assign this number, and
          the request from the registrant will use TBD1 instead of an
          actual value.  The value assigned must be unique.  A Designated
          Expert must be used to ensure that when the name of the layout
          type and its value are added to the NFSv4.1 layouttype4
          enumerated data type in the NFSv4.1 XDR description (<xref target="I-D.ietf-nfsv4-rfc5662bis-dot-x" />), the
          result continues to be a valid XDR description.
        </t>

        <t>
          The Standards Track RFC(s) that describe the notification.  If
          the RFC(s) have not yet been published, the registrant will use
          RFCTBD2, RFCTBD3, etc. instead of an actual RFC number.
          Collectively, the RFC(s) must adhere to the guidelines listed in
          <xref target="ss:iana_considerations:GfWLTS" />.
        </t>

        <t>
          How the RFC introduces the layout type.  This is indicated by a
          single US-ASCII value.  If the value is N, it means a minor
          revision to the NFSv4 protocol.  If the value is L, it means a
          new pNFS layout type.  Other values can be used with IESG
          Approval.
        </t>

        <t>
          The minor versions of NFSv4 that are allowed to use the
          notification.  While these are numeric values, IANA will not
          allocate and assign them; the author of the relevant RFCs with
          IESG Approval assigns these numbers.  Each time there is a new
          minor version of NFSv4 approved, a Designated Expert should
          review the registry to make recommended updates as needed.
        </t>
      </list>
    </t>

    <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:iana_considerations:IR3" title="Initial Registry">
      <t>
        The initial registry is in <xref target="layoutlist"/>.
      </t>
      <texttable title="Initial Layout Type Assignments" anchor="layoutlist">
        <ttcol>Layout Type Name</ttcol>
        <ttcol>Value</ttcol>
        <ttcol>RFC</ttcol>
        <ttcol>How</ttcol>
        <ttcol>Minor Versions</ttcol>
        <c>LAYOUT4_NFSV4_1_FILES</c> <c>0x1</c> <c>RFC 5661</c> <c>N</c> <c>1</c>
        <c>LAYOUT4_OSD2_OBJECTS</c> <c>0x2</c> <c>RFC 5664</c> <c>L</c> <c>1</c>
        <c>LAYOUT4_BLOCK_VOLUME</c> <c>0x3</c> <c>RFC 5663</c> <c>L</c> <c>1</c>
      </texttable>
    </section>

    <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:iana_considerations:UR3" title="Updating Registrations">
      <t>
        The update of a registration will require IESG Approval on the advice
        of a Designated Expert.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:iana_considerations:GfWLTS" title="Guidelines for Writing Layout Type Specifications">
      <t>
        The author of a new pNFS layout specification must follow these steps
        to obtain acceptance of the layout type as a Standards Track RFC:
      </t>

      <t>
        <list style='numbers'>
          <t>
            The author devises the new layout specification.
          </t>

          <t>
            The new layout type specification MUST, at a minimum:

            <list style='symbols'>
              <t>
                Define the contents of the layout-type-specific fields of the
                following data types:

                <list style='symbols'>
                  <t>
                    the da_addr_body field of the device_addr4 data type;
                  </t>

                  <t>
                    the loh_body field of the layouthint4 data type;
                  </t>

                  <t>
                    the loc_body field of layout_content4 data type (which in
                    turn is the lo_content field of the layout4 data type);
                  </t>

                  <t>
                    the lou_body field of the layoutupdate4 data type;
                  </t>
                </list>
              </t>

              <t>
                Describe or define the storage access protocol used to access
                the storage devices.
              </t>

              <t>
                Describe whether revocation of layouts is supported.
              </t>

              <t>
                At a minimum, describe the methods of recovery from:

                <list style='numbers'>
                  <t>
                    Failure and restart for client, server, storage device.
                  </t>

                  <t>
                    Lease expiration from perspective of the active client,
                    server, storage device.
                  </t>

                  <t>
                    Loss of layout state resulting in fencing of client access
                    to storage devices (for an example, see <xref target="ss:parallel_nfs:DwLoLSotMS" />).
                  </t>
                </list>
              </t>

              <t>
                Include an IANA considerations section, which will in turn
                include:

                <list style='symbols'>
                  <t>
                    A request to IANA for a new layout type per <xref target="ss:iana_considerations:LT" />.
                  </t>

                  <t>
                    A list of requests to IANA for any new recallable object
                    types for CB_RECALL_ANY; each entry is to be presented in
                    the form described in <xref target="ss:iana_considerations:ORT" />.
                  </t>

                  <t>
                    A list of requests to IANA for any new notification values
                    for CB_NOTIFY_DEVICEID; each entry is to be presented in
                    the form described in <xref target="ss:iana_considerations:DIN" />.
                  </t>
                </list>
              </t>

              <t>
                Include a security considerations section.  This section MUST
                explain how the NFSv4.1 authentication, authorization, and
                access-control models are preserved.  That is, if a metadata
                server would restrict a READ or WRITE operation, how would
                pNFS via the layout similarly restrict a corresponding input
                or output operation?
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>

          <t>
            The author documents the new layout specification as an Internet-Draft.
          </t>

          <t>
            The author submits the Internet-Draft for review through the IETF
            standards process as defined in "The Internet Standards Process--
            Revision 3" (BCP 9).  The new layout specification will be
            submitted for eventual publication as a Standards Track RFC.
          </t>

          <t>
            The layout specification progresses through the IETF standards
            process.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section anchor="ss:iana_considerations:PVD" title="Path Variable Definitions">
    <t>
      This section deals with the IANA considerations associated with the
      variable substitution feature for location names as described in
      <xref target="ss:multi-server_namespace:TfS2" />.  As described there, variables subject to
      substitution consist of a domain name and a specific name within that
      domain, with the two separated by a colon.  There are two sets of
      IANA considerations here:
    </t>

    <t>
      <list style='numbers'>
        <t>
          The list of variable names.
        </t>

        <t>
          For each variable name, the list of possible values.
        </t>
      </list>
    </t>

    <t>
      Thus, there will be one registry for the list of variable names, and
      possibly one registry for listing the values of each variable name.
    </t>

    <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:iana_considerations:PVR" title="Path Variables Registry">
      <t>
        IANA created a registry called the "NFSv4 Path Variables Registry".
      </t>

      <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:iana_considerations:PVV" title="Path Variable Values">
        <t>
          Variable names are of the form "${", followed by a domain name,
          followed by a colon (":"), followed by a domain-specific portion of
          the variable name, followed by "}".  When the domain name is
          "ietf.org", all variables names must be registered with IANA on a
          Standards Action basis, with Expert Review required.  Path variables
          with registered domain names neither part of nor equal to ietf.org
          are assigned on a Hierarchical Allocation basis (delegating to the
          domain owner) and thus of no concern to IANA, unless the domain owner
          chooses to register a variable name from his domain.  If the domain
          owner chooses to do so, IANA will do so on a First Come First Serve
          basis.  To accommodate registrants who do not have their own domain,
          IANA will accept requests to register variables with the prefix
          "${FCFS.ietf.org:" on a First Come First Served basis.  Assignments
          on a First Come First Basis do not require Expert Review, unless the
          registrant also wants IANA to establish a registry for the values of
          the registered variable.
        </t>

        <t>
          The registry is a list of assignments, each containing three fields.
        </t>

        <t>
          <list style='numbers'>
            <t>
              The name of the variable.  The name of this variable must start
              with a "${" followed by a registered domain name, followed by
              ":", or it must start with "${FCFS.ietf.org".  The name must be
              no more than 64 UTF-8 characters long.  The name must be unique.
            </t>

            <t>
              For assignments made on Standards Action basis, the Standards
              Track RFC(s) that describe the variable.  If the RFC(s) have not
              yet been published, the registrant will use RFCTBD1, RFCTBD2,
              etc. instead of an actual RFC number.  Note that the RFCs do not
              have to be a part of an NFS minor version.  For assignments made
              on a First Come First Serve basis, an explanation (consuming no
              more than 1024 bytes, or more if IANA permits) of the purpose of
              the variable.  A reference to the explanation can be substituted.
            </t>

            <t>
              The point of contact, including an email address.  The point of
              contact can consume up to 256 bytes (or more if IANA permits).
              For assignments made on a Standards Action basis, the point of
              contact is always IESG.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:iana_considerations:IR4" title="Initial Registry">
          <t>
            The initial registry is in <xref target="varlist"/>.
          </t>

          <texttable title="Initial List of Path Variables" anchor="varlist">
            <ttcol>Variable Name</ttcol>
            <ttcol>RFC</ttcol>
            <ttcol>Point of Contact</ttcol>
            <c>${ietf.org:CPU_ARCH}</c> <c>RFC 5661</c> <c>IESG</c>
            <c>${ietf.org:OS_TYPE}</c> <c>RFC 5661</c> <c>IESG</c>
            <c>${ietf.org:OS_VERSION}</c> <c>RFC 5661</c> <c>IESG</c>
          </texttable>

          <t>
            IANA has created registries for the values of the variable names
            ${ietf.org:CPU_ARCH} and ${ietf.org:OS_TYPE}.  See Sections <xref target="ss:iana_considerations:VftV" format='counter' />
            and <xref target="ss:iana_considerations:VftV1" format='counter' />.
          </t>

          <t>
            For the values of the variable ${ietf.org:OS_VERSION}, no registry is
            needed as the specifics of the values of the variable will vary with
            the value of ${ietf.org:OS_TYPE}.  Thus, values for ${ietf.org:
            OS_VERSION} are on a Hierarchical Allocation basis and are of no
            concern to IANA.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:iana_considerations:UR4" title="Updating Registrations">
          <t>
            The update of an assignment made on a Standards Action basis will
            require IESG Approval on the advice of a Designated Expert.
          </t>

          <t>
            The registrant can always update the point of contact of an
            assignment made on a First Come First Serve basis.  Any other update
            will require Expert Review.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:iana_considerations:VftV" title="Values for the ${ietf.org:CPU_ARCH} Variable">
      <t>
        IANA created a registry called the "NFSv4 ${ietf.org:CPU_ARCH} Value
        Registry".
      </t>

      <t>
        Assignments to the registry are made on a First Come First Serve
        basis.  The zero-length value of ${ietf.org:CPU_ARCH} is Reserved.
        Values with a prefix of "PRIV" are designated for Private Use.
      </t>

      <t>
        The registry is a list of assignments, each containing three fields.
      </t>

      <t>
        <list style='numbers'>
          <t>
            A value of the ${ietf.org:CPU_ARCH} variable.  The value must be
            1 to 32 UTF-8 characters long.  The value must be unique.
          </t>

          <t>
            An explanation (consuming no more than 1024 bytes, or more if
            IANA permits) of what CPU architecture the value denotes.  A
            reference to the explanation can be substituted.
          </t>

          <t>
            The point of contact, including an email address.  The point of
            contact can consume up to 256 bytes (or more if IANA permits).
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:iana_considerations:IR5" title="Initial Registry">
        <t>
          There is no initial registry.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:iana_considerations:UR5" title="Updating Registrations">
        <t>
          The registrant is free to update the assignment, i.e., change the
          explanation and/or point-of-contact fields.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:iana_considerations:VftV1" title="Values for the ${ietf.org:OS_TYPE} Variable">
      <t>
        IANA created a registry called the "NFSv4 ${ietf.org:OS_TYPE} Value
        Registry".
      </t>

      <t>
        Assignments to the registry are made on a First Come First Serve
        basis.  The zero-length value of ${ietf.org:OS_TYPE} is Reserved.
        Values with a prefix of "PRIV" are designated for Private Use.
      </t>

      <t>
        The registry is a list of assignments, each containing three fields.
      </t>

      <t>
        <list style='numbers'>
          <t>
            A value of the ${ietf.org:OS_TYPE} variable.  The value must be 1
            to 32 UTF-8 characters long.  The value must be unique.
          </t>

          <t>
            An explanation (consuming no more than 1024 bytes, or more if
            IANA permits) of what CPU architecture the value denotes.  A
            reference to the explanation can be substituted.
          </t>

          <t>
            The point of contact, including an email address.  The point of
            contact can consume up to 256 bytes (or more if IANA permits).
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:iana_considerations:IR6" title="Initial Registry">
        <t>
          There is no initial registry.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:iana_considerations:UR6" title="Updating Registrations">
        <t>
          The registrant is free to update the assignment, i.e., change the
          explanation and/or point of contact fields.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
