<!-- Copyright (C) The IETF Trust (2011) -->
<!-- Copyright (C) The Internet Society (2011) -->

  <section anchor="op_OPENATTR" title="Operation 19: OPENATTR - Open Named Attribute Directory">
    <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:op_OPENATTR:A" title="ARGUMENT">
      <?rfc include='autogen/openattr_args.xml'?>
    </section>

    <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:op_OPENATTR:R" title="RESULT">
      <?rfc include='autogen/openattr_res.xml'?>
    </section>

    <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:op_OPENATTR:D" title="DESCRIPTION">
      <t>
        The OPENATTR operation is used to obtain the filehandle of the named
        attribute directory associated with the current filehandle.  The
        result of the OPENATTR will be a filehandle to an object of type
        NF4ATTRDIR.  From this filehandle, READDIR and LOOKUP operations can
        be used to obtain filehandles for the various named attributes
        associated with the original file system object.  Filehandles
        returned within the named attribute directory will designate objects
        of type of NF4NAMEDATTR.
      </t>

      <t>
        The createdir argument allows the client to signify if a named
        attribute directory should be created as a result of the OPENATTR
        operation.  Some clients may use the OPENATTR operation with a value
        of FALSE for createdir to determine if any named attributes exist for
        the object.  If none exist, then NFS4ERR_NOENT will be returned.  If
        createdir has a value of TRUE and no named attribute directory
        exists, one is created and its filehandle becomes the current
        filehandle.  On the other hand, if createdir has a value of TRUE and
        the named attribute directory already exists, no error results and
        the filehandle of the existing directory becomes the current
        filehandle.  The creation of a named attribute directory assumes that
        the server has implemented named attribute support in this fashion
        and is not required to do so by this definition.
      </t>

      <t>
        If the current file handle designates an object of type NF4NAMEDATTR
        (a named attribute) or NF4ATTRDIR (a named attribute directory), an
        error of NFS4ERR_WRONG_TYPE is returned to the client.  Named
        attributes or a named attribute directory MUST NOT have their own
        named attributes.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section toc='exclude' anchor="ss:op_OPENATTR:I" title="IMPLEMENTATION">
      <t>
        If the server does not support named attributes for the current
        filehandle, an error of NFS4ERR_NOTSUPP will be returned to the
        client.
      </t>
    </section>
  </section>

